<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	   xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	   xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	   xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	   xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	   xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	   xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>(Imperfect Beginnings)</title>
  <atom:link href="http://bathetic.net/imperfect-beginnings.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 23:42:54 -0400</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 May 2016 23:42:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 24.5 Org-mode 8.3.4</generator>
  <webMaster>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>(Imperfect Beginnings)</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  </image>

  <p>

  </p>

  <p>
    I want a perfect start: I want a perfect initial post about a perfectly chosen
    topic to take shape in a perfectly designed site running on a perfectly
    configured implementation of a perfectly crafted framework. I want this
    improbably auspicious beginning because I want to avoid embarrassment, because I
    want to avoid confronting the meagerness of my abilities, and because a
    preoccupation with interminable parameter-fiddling and configuration-setting
    postpones the harder task of crafting content. Similarly, it is
    easier to write about how hard it is to start writing than it is to start
    writing meaningful things. But once one has begun that easier bit, a beginning
    has been made all the same!
  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      perfect (adj.): 
    </p>

    <p>
      early 15c. alteration of Middle English <i>parfit</i> (c. 1300), from
      Old French <i>parfit</i> "finished, completed, ready" (11c.), from Latin <i>perfectus</i>
      "completed, excellent, accomplished, exquisite," past participle of <i>perficere</i>
      "accomplish, finish, complete," from <i>per-</i> "completely" (see per) + <i>facere</i>
      "to make, do, perform" (see factitious). 
    </p>

    <p>
      — <a href="http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=perfect&amp;allowed_in_frame=0">etymonline.com</a>
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>
    According to the <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/etymon">etyma</a> of 'perfect' a "perfect beginning" is an oxymoron. But
    our words don't mean what philologists think their roots meant millennia ago:
    everybody knows a <i>perfect beginning</i> is an <i>optimal starting condition</i>; no
    one thinks it is the paradox of an initiation simultaneously completing itself.
  </p>

  <p>
    I have always had too much trouble getting projects started, and even more
    trouble keeping them underway. However, I am finally learning that any starting
    conditions that will enable me to move forward are good enough (thanks Andrew
    and Kat!). So this thing here—be it blog, website, notebook, or something
    else—is starting as a sketchy skeleton, barely formed, and maybe even malformed,
    but it is underway all the same!
  </p>

  <p>
    A reader who follows the development of this space will see it gradually take
    shape, steadily changing form until it reaches its inevitably imperfect final
    state. I can safely say, perfection will be found neither at the beginning nor at
    the end, but maybe some bits and fragments will seem to find a perfect fit
    along the way.
  </p>

  <item>
    <title>Plans</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/imperfect-beginnings.html#orgheadline1</link>
    <author>Shon Feder</author>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://bathetic.net/imperfect-beginnings.html#orgheadline1</guid>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 21:43:00 -0400</pubDate>

    <description><![CDATA[<p>
    I end my beginning with a list of some of the things I hope to get done.
  </p>
    ]]></description>
  </item>
</channel>
</rss>
