<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	   xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	   xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	   xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	   xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	   xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	   xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>Reasons We Program: II. What is Programming?</title>
  <atom:link href="http://bathetic.net/reasons-we-program-2.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 21:54:05 -0400</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2017 21:54:05 -0400</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 25.1 Org-mode 8.3.5</generator>
  <webMaster>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>Reasons We Program: II. What is Programming?</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  </image>

  <p>
    I reorient this exposition by reiteration my central excerpt, and then giving it
    a close, point-by-point exegesis:
  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      Educators, generals, dieticians, psychologists, and parents program. Armies,
      students, and some societies are programmed. An assault on large problems
      employs a succession of programs, most of which spring into existence en
      route. These programs are rife with issues that appear to be particular to the
      problem at hand. To appreciate programming as an intellectual activity in its
      own right you must turn to computer programming; you must read and write
      computer programs -- many of them. It doesn't matter much what the programs
      are about or what applications they serve. What does matter is how well they
      perform and how smoothly they fit with other programs in the creation of still
      greater programs. The programmer must seek both perfection of part and
      adequacy of collection. In this book the use of ``program'' is focused on the
      creation, execution, and study of programs written in a dialect of Lisp for
      execution on a digital computer. Using Lisp we restrict or limit not what we
      may program, but only the notation for our program descriptions. — <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-5.html">SICP</a>
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <div class="org-src-container">
    <label class="org-src-name">Vimish recipe for splitting a paragraph into lines of blockquoted sentences:</label>
    <pre class="src src-aside">vip:s/\./\.\n#+END_QUOTE\n\n#+BEGIN_QUOTE\n/
    </pre>
  </div>

  <p>
    Who is that programs?
  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      Educators, generals, dieticians, psychologists, and parents program.
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>
    Here we have a list of some of the kinds of people who
    practice programming. All manner of individuals in all kinds of occupations,
    professional, militant, and personal, engage in programming.
  </p>

  <p>
    What gets programmed?
  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      Armies, students, and some societies are programmed.
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <p>
    Collective organizations.
  </p>

  <p>
    What is programming used for?
  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      An assault on large problems employs a succession of programs, most of which
      spring into existence en route.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      These programs are rife with issues that appear to be particular to the problem
      at hand.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      To appreciate programming as an intellectual activity in its own right you must
      turn to computer programming; you must read and write computer programs -- many
      of them.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      It doesn't matter much what the programs are about or what applications they
      serve.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      What does matter is how well they perform and how smoothly they fit with other
      programs in the creation of still greater programs.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      The programmer must seek both perfection of part and adequacy of collection.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      In this book the use of ``program'' is focused on the creation, execution, and
      study of programs written in a dialect of Lisp for execution on a digital
      computer.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <blockquote>
    <p>
      Using Lisp we restrict or limit not what we may program, but only the notation
      for our program descriptions.
    </p>
  </blockquote>


  <item>
    <title>What is Programming?</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/reasons-we-program-2.html#orgheadline1</link>
    <author>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</author>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://bathetic.net/reasons-we-program-2.html#orgheadline1</guid>
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 09:35:00 -0500</pubDate>

    <description><![CDATA[<p>
    Computation is the autonomous part of inscription; it is the immanent
    self-determination of writing. We seize on computation when we confine writing
    to an exact description of what and where it is itself is inscribed. Computing
    is the writing that reads and rewrites itself. The computer is the agent who
    mediates this autonomous developing.
    </p>

    <p>
    The programmatic is that which can be written out in advance. A program sets out
    in writing what is to be done. Executing a program means reading what was
    written and enacting the plan described. Computation is where the programmatic
    comes into what is essentially its own: what was written in advance users a
    computer to read and execute itself.
    </p>

    <div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-3">
    <h3 id="orgheadline1"><a id="ID-87A90B6B-2421-4358-95A5-65560B1597AE"></a><span class="section-number-3">1.1</span> What is it?</h3>
    <div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-1">
    </div>
    </div>

    <div id="outline-container-orgheadline1" class="outline-3">
    <h3 id="orgheadline1"><a id="ID-4E82E363-7723-4533-BB36-B420E5F03B6F"></a><span class="section-number-3">1.2</span> Programming and computation</h3>
    <div class="outline-text-3" id="text-1-2">
    <blockquote>
    <p>
    Now all rational cognition is either cognition from concepts or cognition
    from the construction of concepts; the former is called philosophical and the
    latter mathematical.
    </p>

    <p>
    — Kant, B865
    </p>
    </blockquote>
    </div>
    </div>
    ]]></description>
  </item>
</channel>
</rss>
