<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	   xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	   xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	   xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	   xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	   xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	   xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	   xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
     xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
     xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel>
  <title>Why We Program: I. How ask "Why"?</title>
  <atom:link href="http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
  <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
  <language>en</language>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 20:14:03 -0500</pubDate>
  <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 20:14:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
  <generator>Emacs 25.1 Org-mode 8.3.5</generator>
  <webMaster>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</webMaster>
  <image>
    <url>http://orgmode.org/img/org-mode-unicorn-logo.png</url>
    <title>Why We Program: I. How ask "Why"?</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/</link>
  </image>

  <p>

  </p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>
      Educators, generals, dieticians, psychologists, and parents program. Armies,
      students, and some societies are programmed. An assault on large problems
      employs a succession of programs, most of which spring into existence en route.
      These programs are rife with issues that appear to be particular to the problem
      at hand. To appreciate programming as an intellectual activity in its own right
      you must turn to computer programming; you must read and write computer programs
      …
    </p>

    <p>
      — Ableson, Sussman, and Sussman, <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book-Z-H-5.html#%_chap_Temp_2">SICP</a>
    </p>
  </blockquote>

  <item>
    <title>Rationale</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline1</link>
    <author>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</author>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline1</guid>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 18:16:00 -0500</pubDate>

    <description><![CDATA[<p>
    <b>What this is:</b> A confession of the reasons I program and of my motives for embracing or
    eschewing those reasons.
    </p>

    <p>
    <b>Why this is:</b> <i>For the non-programmer</i>, it is an exposition of some of the
    thoughts and motives of a programming enthusiast, and perhaps a seduction to
    try programming yourself. <i>For the programmer</i>, working or playing, I have two
    aims in mind:
    </p>

    <ul class="org-ul">
    <li>An invitation to consider, or reconsider, your own reasons and motives for programming.</li>
    <li>A request for commentary or critique on the notions I've presented here.</li>
    </ul>
    ]]></description>
  </item>

  <item>
    <title>On rationale</title>
    <link>http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline3</link>
    <author>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</author>
    <guid isPermaLink="false">http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline3</guid>
    <pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 09:15:00 -0500</pubDate>

    <description><![CDATA[<p>
    What does this mean: "to have a reason for doing something"? When we take this
    to be a matter of motive, fitting answers take shape:
    </p>

    <ul class="org-ul">
    <li>money</li>
    <li>pleasure</li>
    <li>power</li>
    <li>status</li>
    <li>edification</li>
    <li>etc.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    <i>Motive</i> was a matter of setting things in motion:
    </p>

    <blockquote>
    <p>
    mid-14c., "something brought forward," from Old French <i>motif</i> "will, drive,
    motivation," noun use of adjective, literally "moving," from Medieval Latin
    <i>motivus</i> "moving, impelling," from Latin <i>motus</i> "a moving, motion," past
    participle of <i>movere</i> "to move". Meaning "that which inwardly
    moves a person to behave a certain way" is from early 15c.
    </p>

    <p>
    — <a href="http://etymonline.com/index.php?term=motive&amp;allowed_in_frame=0">Etymonline</a>
    </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>
    These refracted reflections on my reasons for programming are modulated by the
    impulses that direct my intention — base and baseless alike. But this kind
    of <i>reason</i> isn't the one I'm really interested in.
    </p>

    <div id="outline-container-orgheadline2" class="outline-3">
    <h3 id="orgheadline2"><a id="ID-925F3F8A-F4DB-4146-96DB-7D6AF1EE7942"></a><span class="section-number-3">2.1</span> Historical and rational cognition</h3>
    <div class="outline-text-3" id="text-2-1">
    <p>
    Like the impulses that set matter in motion, motivating inclinations are
    contingent, <i>historical</i> components of organized action. Such inclinations
    are produced by contingent, historical cognitions. These tell us something
    about the conditions and circumstances surrounding the action and the actor
    but they don't reveal anything about the <i>fundamental</i> structures that
    organize and sustain the circumstance.
    </p>

    <blockquote>
    <p>
    If I abstract from all content of cognition, objectively considered, then all
    cognition, considered subjectively, is either historical or rational.
    Historical cognition is <i>cognitio ex datis</i>, rational cognition however,
    <i>cognitio ex principiis</i>. However a cognition may have been given originally,
    it is still historical for him who possesses it if he cognizes it only to the
    degree and extent that it has been given to him from elsewhere, whether it
    has been given to him through immediate experience or told to him or even
    given to him through instruction (general cognitions) … He has formed himself
    according to an alien reason, but the faculty of imitation is not that of
    generation, i.e., the cognition did not arise <b>from</b> reason for him, and
    although objectively it was certainly a rational cognition, subjectively it
    is still merely historical.
    </p>

    <p>
    — Kant, <i>Critique of Pure Reason</i>
    </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>
    Suppose, as Abelson and the Sussmans claim, that computer programming stages
    an encounter with the essential structure of programming and programmability.
    Then computer programming would enable rational cognition of programming and
    an understanding of the subject matter on the basis of its fundamental
    principles, <i>cognitio ex principiis</i>. In contrast, experience with the
    informal programs of the educator, general, and dietician would provide a
    merely historical cognition of programming. The latter only gives us
    understanding relative to the programmable domain that happens to be given in
    the course of our practical experience. Such understanding, <i>cognitio ex
    datis</i>, would be bound and determined by the contingencies of whatever we
    were given, and it would be would be "rife with issues that appear to be
    particular to the problem at hand".
    </p>

    <p>
    But the same can be said of reflexive understanding that seeks cognition of
    the reasons for pursuing "programming as an intellectual activity in its own
    right". If we settle for an account of the historical circumstances that
    determined our practice, and fixate on a taxonomy of the extraneous desires
    that motivate our interest, we'll have merely historical understanding of our
    reasons for programming.
    </p>

    <blockquote>
    <p>

    </p>

    <p>
    The historical approach, that seeks to eavesdrop on the becoming of things
    and from becoming to know their essence, certainly carries great authority;
    but it has also its limitations. If in the existing flux of all things there
    is nothing fixed, eternity persists, then the knowability of the world would
    end and everything would plummet into confusion. One thinks, as it appears,
    that concepts in the individual mind emerge like the leaves on trees, and
    believes that their nature could be recognized from this, that one explores
    and seeks to define their emergence psychologically from the nature of the
    human mind. But this conception pushes everything into the subjective, and if
    pursued to the end, annihilates truth. What one calls the history of concepts
    is rather either a history of our knowledge of concepts or of the meanings of
    words. 
    </p>

    <p>
    — Frege, <i>The Foundations of Arithmetic</i>
    </p>
    </blockquote>

    <p>
    I <i>will</i> note some highlights in the historical determination of my
    preoccupation with programming, but these reflections on why we program aim
    to remark essential features of the relation between instrumental reason and
    computer programming. The grounding principle from which this understanding
    struggles to take shape is the inherent correspondence between the basic
    nature of calculative reason, formalized in computation, and the essentially
    programmatic nature of all instrumentation.
    </p>
    </div>
    </div>
    ]]></description>
</item>

<item>
  <title>The program</title>
  <link>http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline4</link>
  <author>sf@comp.local (Shon Feder)</author>
  <guid isPermaLink="false">http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html#orgheadline4</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 18:05:00 -0500</pubDate>

  <description><![CDATA[<ul class="org-ul">
  <li><a href="http://bathetic.net/why-we-program-i.html">I. How ask "Why"?</a></li>
  <li>II. What is Programming?</li>
  <li>III. Reasons</li>
  </ul>
  ]]></description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
